[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
e-r. SC radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host Gregory cap Hammer
today's guest is Wolf vulk the CEO and
founder of prefix dodev he is is the
creator of both the Mamba package
manager implemented in C++ and the pixie
package manager implemented in Rust wolf
is also the creator of numerous packages
on cond Forge a core member of the cond
forge team and the founder of the
robotack project welcome to software
engineering radio wolf thanks for having
me I'm very excited to be here I'm glad
you're here today during our episode
we're going to be talking about rust
based tooling for the Python programming
language to keep our conversation
concrete we're going to focus on the
pixie package manager to get our
conversation started I have a two-part
question the first part is what is the
pixie package manager and then secondly
wolf why did you choose to implement it
in Rust excellent questions so for pixie
we actually starting to also call it the
workflow manager so it's not just a
package manager and pixie is a project
that we've recently started to kind of
kick off the next Next Generation
package management for the cond
ecosystem and we are sitting on top of
the or standing on top of the shoulders
of the entire existing cond or ecosystem
and so all the packages that already
exist are compatible with Pixie and
pixie gives you a very modern workflow
to work with
projects uh using these operating system
agnostic packages in a way so you can
easily manage your project on Windows
Mac OS and Linux using pixie as a
package manager and it's also at the
same time through the roots of our like
cond Heritage in a way we have a very
tight integration with the python
ecosystem as well and yeah pixie
basically lets you first of all manage
your packages and dependencies then
create some crossplatform tasks that you
can easily execute on any computer with
the idea that all you have to do is get
clone my project and then pixie Run
start and that will do all the magic
that's necessary to kind of get your
project up and running on that computer
that you are on that sounds really
interesting wolf we're going to dive
into the specific details of the pixie
workflow management system before we go
into the details can you tell us why did
you choose to implement it in Rust yeah
for sure so we actually started out with
our low-level libraries and they are
called rler and rler implements they
rust crates which is just a rust word
for libraries I think and the redl
project essentially implements
everything you need to deal with cona
packages so downloading what's called
repo data to installing the packages
into a Target environment and doing
everything in between is implemented in
that low-level library and this library
is actually used across all of our
projects so on our website
in pixie and so the first motivation for
like using rust here was that we could
easily use it also in our server back
end because before I was implement or I
was developing a lot on Mamba and Mamba
has a C++ sort of library in the back
and that was not easy to use in a server
environment because of the memory safety
issues of C++ and actually there's not
such an extensive ecosystem of like
server libraries in C++ and it's much
easier to kind of do that with rust in
my experience all right thank you for
that response we're going to start
talking a little bit about some of the
Python tools and the python ecosystem
and then later we're going to
investigate the specifics of how you
built your systems using rust so let's
start with some of the basics of python
package management there's a couple
tools that I think we should discuss I
anticipate some of our listeners will
know about them but wolf if you could
give an intro what are the tools that
are called pip and pipex and how do
developers use those yeah so pip is sort
of the I don't know grandfather is maybe
the wrong word but one of the basic
package managers in the pipi ecosystem
and the pipi ecosystem again is
something else than the cona ecosystem
the pipi stands for python package index
and it's basically Community managed
website that hosts all of the Python
packages more or less in existence and
it's it's very easy to just upload and
self-publish your own package to the
python package index it's very widely
used by python developers and pip is
sort of the premere tool like the
community standard tool I would say to
install these packages but it's also
well I don't want to
say simple is the wrong word but it
implements a very barebones kind of
experience it just basically fetches
packages and installs them
while other package managers maybe do
some more things like lock files but
we'll talk about that later I guess and
then pip X is a tool to take to make
packages globally available on your CLI
so that you can pipex coway or something
like this and C is just a fun executable
and when you install that with X it will
be available on your comment line and
you can just use it as if you would have
installed it with ap get or something
like this systemwide yeah thanks for
those responses let's talk now about
some perhaps slightly more modern python
package management tools the two that
come to my mind or pipm and poetry can
you talk a little bit about how those
tools work so the honest answer is that
I haven't extensively use either of
those two
tools okay that's fine I know a few
things about poetry at least because
when we develop pixie we looked at their
implementations quite a bit and poetry
has one really nice feature which is
lock files
and I already mentioned that before log
files basically record exactly the
package versions that you are using at
the time when you were executing
something like poetry install I assume
and this record is great because then
you can easily share it with your
collaborators and they will get the same
versions that you have running on your
system and you're not going to run into
any conflicts based on using different
versions and maybe producing different
results or running into a bug and stuff
like this thanks for that respon about
poetry I agree one of the cool things
about the tool is that it first of all
adheres to the Pi Project toml standard
in many ways and second of all it has
those lock files that you mentioned that
support reproducible builds what I'd
like to do now is turn our attention to
cond and Mamba once again can you tell
us a little bit about these tools and
how they fit into the python ecosystem
definitely so K and Mamba are two tools
that also work in the K ecosystem that's
like the the sort of bigger term here
and Mamba is reimplementation of all the
principles of K but in C++ and K was one
of the first package managers that
basically brought binary packages to the
python ecosystem so that was before
Wheels were a thing but fundamentally
cond also works quite different from
python packages or specifically the pipi
index because with cond you have
channels that are repositories that's
more modeled after like a Linux
distribution where all the packages have
to work together and be compatible with
each other so the cond ecosystem has
somewhat long history I think it's been
definitely over 10 years by now and they
are fundamentally if you look at them
the cona packages themselves are binary
packages that work on multiple platforms
so you have Windows Linux and Mac
support and now more specifically cona
has a very rich tradition in the
scientific Pyon ecosystem because you
usually combine python with C++ or code
or foron even and that has been
traditionally very difficult to support
on the Pyon package index and so cond
has evolved alongside that what we are
trying to do is get it even more
widespread into more ecosystems but I'm
going coming to that later on as well
and Mamba so at some point K became very
slow because one of the fundamental
things that K does is to use a
satisfiability solver to figure out all
the dependencies of a package and all
the matching versions and there's a lot
of things that I have to explain but K
Forge is one of the largest channels and
channels is one repository K Forge is a
big open source Community with over
5,000 members and it had some experience
some exponential growth essentially
because more and more packages and
package versions were added and cond
became really really slow
unbearable even and what I did is over a
weekend sort of sat down tried some
tools from the Linux ecosystem which is
especially lip solve and used lip solve
as an alternative s solver in cond to
get higher speed and Mamba as a result
of that work where essentially we Ed lip
solve to really drastically speed up
cond and nowadays I'm happy to report
that lip solve and lip Mamba actually is
integrated into cond so that all cond
users can experience that speed thanks
for that response you mentioned that one
of the challenges a python programmer
might face if they were using cond was
something that was related to
Performance and I should note that later
we're going to talk about the details
that are related to sat solving and how
you do that in Rust with a certain
package that you integrated into pixie
but before we get into the details about
rust Bas tooling with Pixie can you
comment on any other challenges that a
programmer May face when they're using
these existing python package management
tools so if you use some of the more
simple tools like pip and pip X you
might run into performance problems as
well because there are some challenges
that we also discovered during our work
in the pipi ecosystem where package
metad data is just very difficult to
kind of solve for in the python
ecosystem itself so on pii you might
face issues with version compatibility
and ABI versioning and things like that
that are more consistently manageable
in something like the cond ecosystem
because again in cond you basically use
a channel and the channel is a manag
repository where certain things are kind
of kept in lock step like the compiler
versions the library versions that are
used and the link libraries and all of
this and that's one of the big pluses of
yeah the con ecosystem okay thank you
for sharing those details I want to turn
our attention now to using pixie which
is a tool that you implemented in Rust I
remember you said before that it's for a
whole management of a workflow we're
going to talk about some of the
specifics about how it helps to manage
that workflow one of the things that I
noticed on the website that describes
pixie is that people can use it in a
crossplatform fashion on Windows Mac and
Linux my question is as follows what did
you have to do to make the Tool Work
effectively on three major operating
systems so the majority of work was
already done done because well we are
piggybacking on the cona ecosystem and
cona Forge specifically has a really
large repository of existing packages
and so a lot of the nice tools that we
want to use or our users might want to
use are already available but then there
are some more intricate challenges
because windows and Unix are usually
quite different and especially there is
no bash or not really a good bash on
Windows except for git bash but it's not
really like tightly integrated into the
operating system
and so what we're doing is we are
actually using something from the
node.js community specifically from Dino
it's called Doo task shell and for our
crossplatform tasks it basically takes
something that looks like a small bash
snippet but executes it in its own shell
and that's one of the things where we
were really happy to use rust because we
could just reuse an existing Library
there aha so this highlights one of the
benefits of using rust in order to build
pixie another thing that I noticed is
that you say that pixie can be used to
install both libraries and
applications can you talk a little bit
about the distinctions between a library
and an application so just generally one
of the features of Pixie is that you can
do pixie Global install that is very
similar to pipx which we discussed
before where you if you install
something globally it puts an executable
on your path and that means from
anywhere on your system you can use it
and so that is something that you would
would use for applications that you want
to have globally available that are not
Project Specific Etc on the other hand
libraries so we manage loads of
libraries on the cona Forge Channel and
those are tools that you use inside of
your project to link against on the
basis of sort of code and so you would
add these development libraries like
numai for example it's not really an
application it's a library that you use
to some array Computing and so yeah that
that's what you would use in your
projects and for the projects you can
either use a pixie. TL file or P project
Tel file and Define all your
dependencies there and then get them
okay you mentioned these Tomo files and
perhaps that connects to my next
question I wanted to talk a little bit
about
reproducibility it seems that
reproducibility is at the core of Pixie
can you explain what is this
reproducibility why is it important and
how does pixie provide it so I think
reproducibility is important in many
ways
first of all there's a big talk about
reproducible
builds and that's also something that we
want to support with red La for example
is that you can be really sure that you
know you can reproduce this exact
program on your computer if you compile
something Etc and then on the other hand
as I mentioned before cond is big in the
scientific ecosystems and
reproducability in scientific world is
also a big problem and with Pixie we
want to make sure that the scientist
that uses pixie can get the same results
now and then also get the same results
in 10 years if you run the same data
pipelines and things like this and we
make sure of that by creating a very
tight lock file that locks down packages
down to the
shahash and the other magic ingredient
here is that the cona Forge ecosystem
never deletes any old packages so that
means our Channel or the con for channel
is growing so of unbounded uh it's
currently at 12 terabytes or something
but it also means that you can reach
back and get the packages from like a
few years ago or you could even get
Python 2.7 if you really wanted to yeah
what you're describing is an incredible
feature of cond thank you for sharing
that detail one of the things I also
note as a python programmer myself is
that it's really important to create a
certain kind of isolated environment
sometimes people call that a virtual
environment is it possible to create
these virtual environments with
Pixie yes very much so at the basis of
cond is also the idea of these
environments they go a bit further than
in the python ecosystem because we also
put any shared libraries and everything
into the virtual environments you
essentially get an entire unit prefix in
your cond environment or pixie
environment and with Pixie so even if
you globally install a package it lives
in its own en environment is sort of
isolated from all the other tools that
you globally install and then
additionally when you create your pixie
project so pixie TL or P project TL file
you can create one or multiple
environments for this project and they
are local to your project they live in a
pixie folder and you can have for
example one environment that's just your
default environment that's the one that
you always get to sort of run your
project and then you can create multiple
additional environments for example for
testing or for linting or for all these
kinds of more specific tasks that you
might want to do but that are not really
required for the average user of your
project for
example that's interesting I wanted to
pick up on something that you talked
about a moment ago in the context of
reproducibility if I'm understanding
correctly I think pixie actually
packages a version of python along with
a project is that true yes that's very
much true and that's also one of the
core things of the cond ecosystem you
can not only get python packages but you
can also get python and a load of
different other tools like r or C++
compilers forun compilers number of
modern languages like rust or go or Nim
or Zig all of these are packaged on con
Forge and all of these can be used in
your projects essentially so it's it
goes beyond sort of just python but ah
to really sort of C capture the entirety
of the Pyon ecosystem you also need to
kind of have a c or C++ compiler
essentially because as I said a lot of
the Python tools are have C or C++
extensions and so in the cond ecosystem
we manage all of them so from the
perspective of having an isolated
reproducible build environment why is it
important to package these programming
languages along with the actual
application that you're building it's
important for for as a distribution it
might not be important for your
application itself but the benefits for
us are that you can get the compilers
and all the control over the compilers
for example at the time when we are
building the packages for distribution
later on and so as con Forge we manage
exactly the version of the for example C
compiler that is used and then we build
for example the python extensions with
that compiler and the reproducibility
comes in because for example a new
compiler might change the output of your
build and when I say reproducible builds
the idea is that you really get bit
forbit compe or equivalent builds even
if you're running on different machines
and that's what we are sort of striving
for where you can get exactly the same
builds and our way of doing that is by
controlling tightly the cona packages
that are used in the versions and then
making sure if I'm understanding you
correctly it sounds like the behavior of
my scientific application should be
exactly the same yes whether I run it on
Windows or Mac OS or Linux is that
correct that's almost correct so I mean
that's the ideal case for sure but we
cannot control the differences between
compilers on different operating systems
because we actually using different
so if you have some C code it might
actually have different optimizations
enabled on Mech OS on clang on arm
processors versus Intel processors and
things like this so I cannot give you
that guarantee but ideally it should be
true that's a really wonderful comment I
think what you're telling me here is
that you're still dependent on the
idiosyncrasies associated with compilers
for different operating
systems okay what I want to do now is to
turn our attention to other types of
package managers like for example we
talked about previously poetry or pipm
if I'm remembering correctly languages
like poetry do not actually bundle the
Python language or a C++ compiler
directly with the package itself and in
fact poetry assumes that you have to
install python on your own first can you
briefly comment why could that be
challenging for a python developer it's
definitely challenging because if you
want to support your users on that
journey and they want to use your
project on uh operating system that you
don't know you first have to figure out
how you can get python on that operating
system and and yeah I think that's one
of the bigger hurdles for adoption and
that's one of the things that rust for
example has solved in a relatively nice
way um by creating something called rust
up just run rust up and you get some
version of rust whether it's on Windows
Mac OS or Linux and I think the python
Community currently lacks this little
bit and then the second challenge is
that your project might want to use the
latest features and requires Pyon 3.12
and now I don't know if the Windows app
store has python 3.12 or what version
they are on or Homebrew or a number of
these different system level package
managers thanks for sharing that point I
agree if you have to install python
yourself you can often run into a whole
bunch of challenges I know that there
are some tools that try to step into the
Gap in order to address those challenges
maybe systems like ASDF or you could use
RTX or I know some people use the Nyx
language or the Nyx pack manager can you
briefly comment how do tools like NYX or
ASDF or RTX fit into this picture that
we're developing yeah so they are pretty
different tools I would say so ASDF as
far as I know basically knows how to get
a number of different tools like you can
get node.js or python or maybe rust or
other sort of lower level system tools
that you want independently of your
operating system but they basically
basically take the releases from some
official I guess repository or GitHub
releases or something like this NYX is
pretty different in that respect because
NYX is a software distribution very
similar or not very similar but similar
to K Forge they have their own recipes
they do their own compilation of all of
the different tools and you basically
buy into a software distribution that is
also hosted on GitHub so there is one
big NYX packages repository that has all
these
recipes and when you get for example I
don't know nodejs or python from NYX it
might be compiled on your own system or
it might use some sort of global cache
of all the Nyx packages that are
available but these are not from the
official releases but they come from
sort of the Nyx
maintainers and that's much more similar
to K Forge where we try to build all the
packages ourselves on CI Pipelines
thanks for illustrating some of the
connections between NYX and cond Forge
and then explaining a little bit about
how ASDF Works I'd like to turn our
attention to pixie which is the rust
based package manager and workflow
manager that we're talking about now I
think it's helpful for us to walk
through some of the steps that a python
developer might follow through and it
would be really helpful wolf in addition
to commenting on what you would do to
achieve that step if you could tell us a
few technical details about how pixie
actually achieves that goal so let's
start with the first step I'm assuming
that if I'm a python programmer and I'm
using pixie somehow I have to initialize
my project can you briefly comment on
how I do that using pixie and then again
how does pixie achieve that goal so
maybe we should start with the first
step which is to install pixie here on
some systems you might be lucky and you
can just use something like brew and
stall pixie which is using another
package manager to get another package
manager which is kind of funny but
that's one way and the other way that
works on all operating systems is to use
the command that we have on our
documentation which is pixie. sh and
then you can use Curl and Bash to
basically download the version of Pixie
and run it and after that you can use
pixie self update to update your pixie
version easily now if you want to start
a project using pixie you first have to
decide is it a python project then you
can use py project. tumn or you can just
use a pixie. 5 for python projects or
anything else and so we recently adopted
the PIP project. standard specifically
for python users but as I mentioned
before pixie is sort of more Universal
so we also have our own format and the
way that works is you do pixie in it
that will create an empty folder with
the pixie TL file inside and then you
can start filling out some metadata
about your project for example the
author the version description and these
kind of things things and that's copied
a little bit from a cargo. file that's
used in the rust community and then the
key thing is that you can Define your
tasks and your dependencies and now in
your dependencies you can basically
specify python as a dependency and the
python version that you want to use and
the rest of your dependencies can be
things like Panda naai jupyter notebooks
etc etc and then there are two more
things that you need to specify so the
first one is you need to have an
understanding of the platforms that you
want your project to run on so by
default pixie will use your current
platform so I'm using a M1 Apple silicon
computer and so that is the OSX arm 64
platform but you might also want your
colleagues that are using Linux or
Windows to use your project and then you
would add
win64 or Linux 64 a Linux Arch 64 and
all these kind of different platforms
that you might want your project run on
and then all you need to do is basically
pixie install or pixie run python or
things like this and that will just
install all the dependencies make sure
that your lock file is up to date write
out a new pixie. loock file if that's
not the case and run your
tools okay thank you for explaining that
I know that many tools in the python
ecosystem have a distinction between
application dependencies and development
dependencies and and I think you hinted
at this previously does pixie provide
this feature and if so can you develop
and explain a little bit more about it
with Pixie you can have just regular
dependencies that those are added to
your default environment and then you
can add any number of your own
individual environments with more like
developer Focus dependencies so let's
say you want some tools to lint your
recipes or run tests and things like
this then you can use specific developer
environments like def environments and
adding to that so the way that works in
pixie right now is that you first Define
features and then you define
environments and you combine one or more
features to create an environment and
that's a bit of an maybe interesting
idea that we have there which is that
you can say okay I have a feature that
is test and that will add pie test to
your dependencies and then you might
have a feature that is pi 311 and Pi 312
and those just depend on two different
versions of python and then you can
create environments that combine those
two features so that would say Okay I
want the test and the pi 31 feature in
my Pi 311 test environment and I want
the test and Pi 312 feature in my Pi 312
test environment what's cool about that
is that you have a very easy way to sort
of build up matrices of things that you
want to test and and a lot of Library
Developers for example they have kind of
different requirements than application
developers an application developer sort
of only cares about running against one
version of python and one version of NPI
or whatever while a library developer
wants to make sure that you know he has
the biggest coverage of the different
configurations that the users could run
in including like testing maybe against
multiple NPI versions multiple python
versions and things like this and so
that's something that you can do with
using these different features and
environments in pixie thanks for sharing
the details about that feature I can
absolutely see how that would be helpful
as you were talking it made me think of
many of the things that I often have to
do when I'm using GitHub actions can you
talk a little bit about how these
features of Pixie might help me when I'm
doing linting or development or testing
inside of a continuous integration
environment so I think like my dream is
that for most projects you wouldn't
really have to write a GitHub actions
file anymore but but instead you would
put everything into a pixie tummel or P
project Tel file that would include all
the tasks that you want to run and all
the dependencies that you need and it
would just breathe through it and you
would just have to do something like
pixie run lint and it exactly does what
you want like lint your program and you
don't need yeah basically debugging
locally is the same as debugging in CI
that's the dream wow that's a really
powerful statement because at that point
I don't have to worry about writing a
program in GitHub actions essentially I
can just have everything specified in my
Pixie setup and then if I understand you
correctly it sounds like everything that
would happen on my laptop is exactly
what would happen in CI is that right
that is exactly like that's part of why
we have the lock file to make sure that
your environment is consistent with the
one that's used in CI okay now what I'd
like to do is to turn our attention to
some more details about implementing
pixie and rust and then we're going to
talk about some of the additional rust
packages that you have built in order to
support the development of Pixie so
first of all one of the things that I
noticed from reading the documentation
about Pixie is that you refer to it as
being a fast tool so I'm wondering can
you briefly tell us what do you mean by
the fact that pixie is fast so one of
the big features sort of of Mamba was
always said it was fast and we know that
people really enjoy a fast tool in their
tool belt and with Pixie we kind of
managed to get it a little faster even
than Mamba which is written in C++ and
already implements a lot of good tricks
and rust really helped there so the idea
is that we really download everything as
parallel as possible and extract it at
the same time as downloading and then
the last step of that process is linking
where you basically take the file and
then create a hard link or reference
into your environment and rust really
helped us there to make everything async
and as parallel as possible okay so you
mentioned async and parallel it sounds
like you're trying to run many different
tasks at the same time on a computer are
there any other specific features of
rust that help you to be fast when it
comes to developing indoor using pixie
so for developing I think it's very fair
to say that the extensive ecosystem of
crates really helps us to be fast in
developing new features and additionally
the r compiler also helps us to be fast
because it makes it relatively easy and
straightforward to for example upgrade
versions of other dependencies and be
sure that if it compiles you have type
safety if it doesn't compile it's like
you already know where to look to fix it
versus with python you maybe only find
out at runtime that something is broken
so that's a big plus and lastly I mean
rust compile down to machine code which
always helps with speed okay so you
mentioned machine code and I absolutely
age with that I quickly wanted to pick
up on the fact that you said that rust
helps our programs to be type safe but
we don't have that same type safety if
we were building the tool in Python
itself can you briefly explore that in
Greater detail what is Type safety and
how does that help you as a rust
programmer who's building
pixie so type safety basically means
that the compiler makes sure that all
the types are declared they are
statically known and we are sure about
the types that we receive in a function
and also that we use to call a function
with where in Python it used to be that
you couldn't even use types really and
then typing got added later on and you
can run tools to analyze your program to
understand whether all the types are as
expected but the rust compiler has a
much stronger sort of
yeah just because of the language and
the sort of specifications of the
language it's much stronger in terms of
yeah checking all the types one of the
things that I think may sound
interesting and yet Perhaps
counterintuitive is that pixie can work
for python development and in fact
development in many other programming
languages but you built it in Rust I
don't want to beg the obvious here but
what led you to pick rust when you
decided to create the pixie system so it
was not initially completely obvious
decision because I already had a lot of
experience with C++ and Mamba and we
could have stick to the C++ ecosystem
but in hindsight I'm very happy that we
chose rust it comes with this Rich
ecosystem it helped us to use the same
sort of underlying code in our website
as well and our platform and we want to
capitalize on that in the future much
more by building awesome services onp on
top of that a lot of the things would
have just been quite a bit harder in C++
and also slower and I don't miss to
debug segmentation faults so I think
that's some of the reasoning that's one
thing I can really connect with I also
don't enjoy debugging segmentation
faults in C or C++ programs I think that
response was very helpful so what I want
to do now is turn our attention to some
of the other rust based tools that
support pixie and the first one that I
remember reading about is something
that's called Rattler build can you tell
us what is Rattler build and how does
that integrate into pixie yeah so it
doesn't really integrate straight away
into pixie as of now but red La is sort
of a companion project that is used to
build the Conor packages in the first
place and we've been really hard at work
on redler bit for the past year or so
and we are relatively close to actually
enable it in the cond Forge distribution
which has a long sort of yeah usage of
cond build and has over 20,000 different
recipes and things like this it's a
large scale project and we've been
gearing up to that moment for a long
time now and hopefully we can get it
over the Finish Line very soon but
basically if you want to create a
package for your own software or someone
else's software you can use rler build
today to compile it and turn it into a
cond package that you can install with
Pixie okay now one of the things I
remember about Rattler build is that it
helps developers to create crossplatform
relocatable binaries can you comment
quickly what does it mean if it's
crossplatform and then perhaps go into
additional detail what does it mean if a
binary is relocatable so crossplatform
in that sense that redler build works on
all the different platforms that we
support So Windows Mac and Linux but you
need to run some what specific code on
each of the platforms sometimes it's
directly translatable sometimes you need
some special handling on Windows Etc but
basically R the build is completely
ready to build your packages for all of
these platforms and then relocat ability
is one of the key features that enables
us to have these virtual environments
and it basically means that you can take
a package that was built by rler build
and install it anywhere on your system
if you take a deban package you cannot
use usually install it anywhere on your
system it has to live in a very specific
place for example SL lip curl or
something like this that's where lip
curl has to be while for us it can be on
any prefix on your system so any virtual
environment and that is enabled by two
tricks one on Mac and one on Linux and
windows Works a bit differently in Linux
we use a tool called patch elf and we
use Pat shelf to take shared library
because we also like shared libraries in
cond OFW as opposed to static libraries
and we use Pat shelf to encode something
that is a relative R path and so the
shared Library will attempt to load
shared libraries that are relative to
itself instead of looking at some
absolute path and we do the same trick
with another tool that's called install
name Tool on Mech OS and we're also
currently in the process of trying to
rewrite those tools and rust so that the
entire experience is more integrated
even
and lastly another trick that we're
using is when we build the package we
install it into a prefix that has a very
very long name it has a insanely long
placeholder and as a last resort what we
can do is at installation time we can
just sort of replace that long string
with the final installation prefix and
those are the two tricks that make the
packages relocatable and the binaries
inside okay thanks for explaining those
tricks both of those make sense to me
before we move on to the next topic I
wanted to make one more point about
Rattler build is this A system that
works for cond and cond Forge and Pipi
or only one of those systems so redler
build only works for cond packages right
now and it's not really intended as
something that works directly for pii
okay I want to turn our attention now to
another system which is called rip when
I learned about rip it said that it was
a library for resolving and installing
python pii packages from rust into a
virtual environment is that the right
understanding and can you develop what
rip does and how it
works yes so rip is a library that's is
also written in Rust and that can
basically resolve packages from Pipi
which works slightly different than cond
and then install the packages into a
virtual environment that's completely
correct and we implemented our own sat
resolver and we made it work pretty
nicely for PPI packages as well where we
had to do some additional modification
specifically for that ecosystem because
contrary so in the cond world what you
get is you get all the repo data all the
index data of all the packages up front
in one gigantic file and on Pipi you
have to grab it yourself piece by piece
and so what we did is we made rip able
to lazily
get the package data and then resolve
the packages Laz you mentioned a moment
ago the concept of sad solving and I
think this would be interesting to
explore in Greater detail can you tell
us what is sat solving and how in the
world does that actually connect to
installing python Pipi packages yeah so
both cond and Pipi use set solvers cond
since a relatively long time or since
the Inception and PPI or Pips
specifically added that later on maybe a
few years ago the idea of set solving is
that you have all of these different
dependencies and dependency specifiers
so for example NPI might depend on
python 3.12 and so on and so that's a
dependency with a dependency specifier
and you want to figure out what version
is compatible with my version of napai
and all the other dependencies that
you've specified and you can translate
that into a satisfiability problem that
is pretty well studied in computer
science with like one small difference
and that you not only want to know if
there's any solution that satisfies your
request like if you ask for numai let's
say but you also want usually you also
want the solution that gives you the
highest versions of all your
dependencies and I think that is roughly
equivalent to something called Max set
which is a set problem that tries to
maximize some cost function or whatever
yeah so so both K and pii use that to
figure out the right packages to install
and they use very different s solver
approaches K historically used some sort
of like different s solvas with their
own kind of extra loops on top to
maximize for some things then in Mamba
we replace that completely with lip
solve which work very nice and in in our
project in pixie we use Rolo which is a
rust library that we've implemented and
that is our s solver and it's based on
lip solve and miniat which is a sort of
widely known I think sat solver that is
easy to understand okay so when you use
this rust based Rolo package inside of
rip the idea is you're trying to find
some package at a specific version that
will work for all the dependency of the
system is that the right way to think
about it that's the right way to think
about it yeah so basically if you
install napai it might depend on a host
of other
libraries and you want to figure out
what are the compatible versions and
what are the maximum compatible versions
that you can get those are the ones you
select okay good now one of the things I
learned about resol is that it supports
something called incremental or lazy
constraint solving why is it necessary
to perhaps be lazy when you're solving
constraints in order to install a
package it's necessary because in the
pipi world you get the metadata not from
one Central index file but from all the
wheels themselves so instead of
downloading one gigantic file you go and
download the first wheel for example
naai in our case and then you look at
the dependencies of naai and then you
recursively fetch the other wheels that
you might need so that takes a while and
to make that faster we don't want to do
that up front we want to sort of have
the resolver guide us on what to
download and yeah that's basically what
resolvable can do is lazily fetch what's
necessary and recently we also made it
async so that you can do that in
parallel with sort of like keeping on
iterating and yeah those are some of the
tricks we Implement for pipia so this is
the second or third time that you
mentioned the idea of a wheel in the
context of python can you comment what
is a wheel and then when you're done
with that can you share a little bit
about how rip looks into the wheel and
then supports this aggressive caching of
pii metadata I can so a wheel is
basically a zip file and it's a newer
format compared to sdis and there was
also something called e files in between
so SDS are just Source distributions
that means no compiled code whatsoever
and they're also the most annoying ones
probably to install because you need to
kind of build them on your own local
machine which takes time and effort and
sometimes gives you
incompatibilities egg files are
completely deprecated you should never
use them and wheels are the modern way
of packaging python programs and they
have some nice properties one is that
they have some more static metadata
inside for sis you first have to build
the sis to kind of understand everything
and like you have to execute the setup.
pipe script sometimes at least to know
the dependencies let's say and with
wheels you have static metadata that you
can just read and then you know the
dependencies the other point is that
Wheels can ship binary artifacts similar
to cond packages actually where you have
shared objects or shared libraries or
executables inside of the wheel files
and you don't have to compile them on
your own machine and so one thing that
we made for example for making wheel
file retrieval very fast and efficient
is that we are reading this it's a zip
file and we reading it I believe from
the end and we read a certain amount of
bytes and we try to get the static
metadata from that amount that we're
reading from the end of the wheel file
without having to download the entire
file and based on that little bit that
we're downloading we can already
determined then whether we have to
download the entire file or what the
dependencies of that file are then we
can already continue and then download
the file and things like this so it's a
way to kind of speed up the process of
getting all the metadata that we need to
be clear when you're talking about
metadata I'm assuming that one part of
the metadata for a package is the
dependencies for that package is that
correct yes okay so then you're
downloading the data you're caching the
data and you're recognizing that you
can't get all the data from one location
it's in individual wheels and then once
you have that you use resolve to perform
constraint solving is that the rough
approximation for the workflow that's
the rough approximation yeah that's
correct okay good so if listeners are
interested in learning about other rust
based programs they may want to listen
to episode 581 where we talk about the
warp Dev terminal window what I want to
do now is to turn our attention to an
opportunity for reflection briefly I
think it would be great wolf if you
could talk a little bit about some of
the key benefits of associated with
building pixie and rler build and rip in
the rust programming language I know
you've hinted it for example type safety
and the development environment are
there other key benefits associated with
using rust to build all of these tools I
think the biggest benefit and I already
mentioned this is the vast ecosystem of
existing crates that are at least to
some degree wellmaintained and you can
get some interesting crates with
interesting features straight away and
just use it in your project that's
really nice I think that's where rust
has more sort of resemblance of maybe
the nodejs npm ecosystem or the python
ecosystem while C++ is really lacking in
that regard like with C++ you maybe get
some bigger libraries but not these kind
of like small nice things memory safety
is a big feature for me really like
statically compiling things is a big one
the async ecosystem of rust is great and
also not really available like that in
C++ yeah Fearless concurrency is one of
the keywords and that is actually pretty
nice yeah wolf thanks for mentioning the
idea of fearless concurrency I can
definitely see how that would help you
to make python tooling that's faster in
Rust what I want to do now is to turn
our attention to some of the drawbacks
associated with using rust did you
notice any drawbacks associated with
picking rust in order to build things
like pixie there's one drawback and
that's always speed of course so the
compilation speed itself is well you
know sometimes you have to wait a few
seconds or half a minute or something
like that for your program to compile
and be ready to like test or or use it's
a relatively new language but not super
new so maybe I think that has pros and
cons in terms of access to like let's
say Talent a lot of people are very
interested in learning rust or using
rust but maybe there's not so many
people that have over 10 years of
experience yeah but it's been a very
good experience so far so I don't really
have many complaints to be honest okay
if a new programmer was just getting
started in order to learn how to program
and rust do you have any advice for them
I think my personal approach is always
to just you know like pick a project try
to do it and experiment with it and
learn by doing basically there's also
the rust programming book which is
freely available online and I have a
copy at home and it helped me getting
started and then and since uh but I'm
sure everybody knows this by now but
chat GPT actually also helped me quite a
bit to really get into rust and these
kind of things and just send your errors
there paste it and then see what it says
and usually it's decent twice aha good
response so what I want to do now is
draw our episode to a conclusion we've
talked about rust based tooling for the
Python programming language and we
focused for example on a tool called
pixie do you have a call to action for
the listeners of software engineering
radio when it comes to either Python
Programming or rust programming I don't
think I have a call to action on that
regard but what I would like all
listeners to do is check out our
documentation on pixie. AG try out pixie
and tell us your feedback we are more or
less 24/7 on Discord and always uh
listening to feedback and ideas and if
you want to do some work on a CLI tool
in Russ then obviously we accept PO
requests and we'd love more Community
contributions okay thank you for that
response I myself can comment that the
Discord Community is really active and
that pixie. sh is a wonderful website so
thank you for creating those Community
Resources as well definitely are there
any other topics that we haven't covered
during the conversation today that you
want to highlight for our listeners I
think I will have to make one statement
which is that we have developed rip and
I talked about it and we're really proud
of it but we actually decided at some
point to switch to another rust based
PPI compatible package manager so in
pixie we are currently integrating with
another toolet called UV so we still
have big hopes in terms of using at some
point the resol library inside of UV
because we think it would be cool but as
of now sort of rip on pause because
basically UV exists and is a rust
implementation of the same ideas as rip
and for us it's easier to sort of
concentrate on making pixie a really
great experience than dealing with
multiple projects at once I remember
reading that announcement about the use
of UV on the website for your company
can you help our listeners to understand
a little bit better what is UV who
created it and then how is it going to
integrate into your tooling yeah so UV
is a pip compatible package manager one
thing that UV did is that it created a
commment line that you can use as a
drop-in replacement for pip or other PPI
tools and it's a rust program it uses a
slightly different sat solver but based
on the similar ideas P grop RS is the
one that they are using and it is a very
nice project has very good sort of
implementation for the caches and things
like this and so it basically gives you
a very decent speed boost over just
using pip and for us it's important to
have a rust native thing that we can use
inside of Pixie to really make sure that
our lock files are the way they should
be and we have the right packages and we
can lock down not only the cond packages
but also the pipi packages and make sure
that everything is consistent and okay
thank you quickly I just wanted to
confirm UV is also implemented in Rust
and it's an open source project
available on GitHub are those points
both right yes and it's made by astral
the company that also created Ruff yes
thanks for mentioning Ruff which is
another tool that also uses the rust
programming language and integrates into
the python ecosystem do you want to
briefly comment what was rough since you
mentioned it a moment ago so rough is a
linter for Python and also a format
so yeah it can replace a number of tools
like flake or pyin and number of others
with one tour that's a lot faster
because it's written in Rust and uses a
different way of parsing Pyon code
essentially okay as we finish our
episode here today if there's a listener
who wants to get started with using
pixie what would you suggest that they
do I would suggest to check out the
documentation we are currently right a
bunch of tutorials that should be
interesting to follow okay thank you for
all of these details about how to build
rust based tooling for the Python
programming language this has been
incredibly helpful and an awesome
conversation if you're a listener who
wants to learn more about programming in
rust or python you're welcome to check
the show notes for additional references
and details wolf thanks again for being
a guest on software engineering radio
thank you all right thanks listeners if
you have any questions or comments would
be delighted to receive them bye
now thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by It
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
c-rnli
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under creative commments
license
2.5 thanks for listening